Alright so we did דף נ"ד *Daf Nun Daled* today and we
start on the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* at the bottom of near the
bottom of נ"ד עמוד ב' *Nun Daled Amud Bet*. We're talking again
about מעשר בהמה Ma'aser Behema. *Ma'aser Behemah* because it's somewhat similar to
a בכור bechor, *Bechor* that as I mentioned both can be eaten
with a מום *Mum* outside of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beis
Hamikdash*. We had mentioned yesterday that the discussion yesterday was in the
ways in which it's parallel to other aspects of מעשר Ma'aser *Ma'aser*
that you do each year separately, you can't take from one year
on the next. You also can't take from one species on the
next, but the way in which מעשר בהמה maaser behemah *Ma'aser Behemah*
is different is that sheep and goat are considered to be one
species which is very unlike what you have by areas like issues
such as grain. So there you can't take from sheep on goat
and vice versa. Now we pick up in our משנה Mishna *Mishnah*,
מעשר בהמה maaser behemah מצטרף כמלא רגל בהמה רועה *Ma'aser Behemah mitztaref
kimlo regel behemah ro'eh*. So you need 10 new animals, 10 new
sheep and goats or 10 new cows in order to be obligated,
right? Anything less than that you wouldn't have to take because it's
each year is separate and if you have less than 10 you
can't take מעשר Ma'aser, *Ma'aser*. Now let's say you have what does
it mean that you've had 10 new animals born to you? Let's
say you have some sheep in Iowa and some in Kansas and
do they all have to get combined? What's considered to be one
flock that has had the new sheep? So here it says that
the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* says that the מעשר בהמה ma'aser behema, *Ma'aser
Behemah* combines by the full of the of the walking of the
animals of the shepherd, which is a little unclear, but now it
tells you what that means and then we'll say how much that
is and then we'll say what it means. וכמה V'kama, היא רגל
בהמה רועה *Vechamah hi regel behemah ro'eh*? And how much is it?
Now רועה *Ro'eh* could also mean the grazing, not the shepherd, the
grazing of the animal. How much is it that the animal the
walk of the animal grazes? שש עשרה מיל mil, *Shesh Esrei
Mil*, 16 מיל mil, *Mil*. Now a מיל mil *Mil* is 2000
אמות amot *Amot*, which is about a kilometer. So it's about 16
kilometers, which is like what like 12 miles or something? Okay so
that's a long distance.
Now why is that the amount? What does that mean the amount
that the animal grazes? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* gives two explanations. One
which makes sense how it could be so long so like 12
miles is that that's how far out of the city you would
take your sheep. Now why you should determine it based on that
is a little bit unclear because the basic issue is you have
some flock over here, some flock 20 miles away or 10 miles
away, are they considered one flock or not? How far you take
them out of the city it's not exactly clear why that should
be the amount that
conceptually joins the two flocks. So the other explanation רש"י Rashi. *Rashi*
has which fits more in what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says but
harder to imagine why this is true is that it's as far
as the shepherd allows his sheep to scatter while he's walking them
that he can see I guess if it's very flat ground or
maybe he's very high up and they're lower he you can see
this far away so you will allow your sheep to scatter that
far within like a radius of well not exactly a radius that's
actually a question if you go in both directions but let's say
the outer edges
are they're within like a what do you call it either from
one sheep to the furthest sheep is this 16 kilometers or that
it's a radius of 16 kilometers which is much larger. Anyway but
if you allow them to scatter that amount and therefore they're different
flocks within that area then they're all considered to be one flock.
But again it's much easier to imagine which is why I assume
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* gave the first explanation that you take them out
of the city 16 kilometers than to say you actually while you're
walking them allow them to scatter that far. But those are the
two explanations and if they're in that amount of distance then they're
all considered to be one flock and any new sheep that are
born to them combine to make the numbers for מעשר בהמה ma'aser
behema *Ma'aser Behemah*. Now היו בין אלו לאלו ל"ב מיל mil. *Hayu
bein elu le'elu lamed bet mil*. Let's say there were 32 מיל
mil *Mil* between them. אין מצטרפין ein mitztarfin, *Ein mitztarfin*, they don't
combine. Obviously anything more than 16 they don't combine. The גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* will ask as if there were 17 מיל mil *Mil* but
the real point is for the next line. היו לו באמצע hayu
lo b'emtza, *Hayu lo be'emtza*. Now somewhere there were 32 מיל mil
*Mil* apart but there were then some sheep right smack in the
middle of those 32 מיל mil. *Mil*. So if you introduce something
in the middle of the 32 there's 16 on each side right?
So היו לו באמצע *Hayu lo be'emtza* and this is where you
sort of get the where you get the idea of the radius
of 16 as long as there's something in the middle okay so
if the two sheep are distant 32 מיל mil. *Mil* you don't
combine them by an imaginary middle point but if there's something in
the middle היו לו באמצע *Hayu lo be'emtza* then if there's sheep
in the middle מביאין באמצע *Mevi'in be'emtza* then you bring them to
the middle רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it doesn't literally mean you bring
them to the middle it means conceptually if they're in the middle
you combine imagine it as if they all combine so if there's
something in the middle 16 אמות amot *Amot* to the left מיל
mil *Mil* to the left 16 מיל mil *Mil* to the right
they're all within 16 מיל *Mil* of the middle so they're all
connected so you can draw a radius as long as there's actually
something in the middle. רבי מאיר אומר הירדן מפסיק למעשר בהמה. Rabbi
Meir omer, HaYarden mafsik lema'aser behemah. He doesn't just disagree with what's
said before, he adds a qualification. He says if someone's on one
side of the Jordan and the others are on the other side
of the Jordan, then they don't combine. The Gemara will discuss whether
that is because practically you cannot easily walk from one side to
the other, or is it because conceptually they're just considered to be
in a different country and that's even if they were within a
close physical distance, if they're considered to be in a different country,
that would there- they would not combine. Yes.
Is עבר הירדן Ever HaYarden really part of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
and would the animals be-
that's what we're going to- well first of all remember the פשט
Pshat even outside. You only have the position of
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
that says that it doesn't and even רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was
qualified by the גמרא Gemara to say you don't bring it as
a קרבן Korban but it still applies. That's true. Okay. So, that's
a good question in general עבר הירדן's Ever HaYarden status for מעשר
Ma'aser? in general. And as- normally we do consider the immediate עבר
הירדן Ever HaYarden is like ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for מעשר, maaser.
תרומות ומעשרות Terumos u'Ma'asros with there are some ways in which it's
different but in general it is. So it's not even a חוץ
לארץ Chutz La'aretz statement here, it's even an עבר הירדן Ever HaYarden
statement. So we'll see more about that when we get to the
גמרא. Gemara Let's first start with the sixteen מיל, sixteen kilometers roughly.
מנא הני מילי, Minani milei, where do you know this from? That-
that-
meaning where do you know not that they can combine but that
they have to be within a certain distance? Meaning maybe I should
just say as long as I own them, even if I have
some in France and some in Kansas. That's what I was- they
all combine, right? Exactly. How do I bring them together to count
מעשר? maaser. Maybe that's my problem, I'm not sure. But at least
in terms of my obligation, it goes by wherever I own them.
How do you know they have to be considered together in one
flock? So, אמר רבה בר שילא דאמר קרא Amar Rava bar Shila
d'amar Kra because the verse says או תעבורנה הצאן על ידי מונה.
os ta'avorna hatzon al yedei moneh. The sheep will pass by through
a counter, one who counts them. So again, תעבור, ta'avor, right, is-
evokes the פסוק Pasuk which is כל אשר יעבור תחת השבט. kol
asher ya'avor tachas hashevet. תחת- Tachas what is it? Ha- yes.
כל אשר יעבור תחת השבט.
Kol asher
ya'avor tachas hashevet. Yeah, right. So it says that you shall pass
them under the- under the rod when you count them and that's
exactly what the מונה moneh is doing, the counter, the person counting
them is counting for the tenth. So we see this as referring
to the- to the- to מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behemah. And you see
that it's sort of speaking- we understand that the verse means that
when are they considered to be one flock? If they can be
counted by one person, if they're in a position to be counted
by one person. וקיימו להו רבנן V'kaimu l'hu Rabbanan and the Rabbis,
you know, have determined דשיתסר מיל כשיעור דעינא דרועה d'shitser mil k'shiur
d'eina d'ro'eh
that sixteen מיל, again roughly sixteen kilometers, is the- is the distance
through which a shepherd can see them. So this is why רש״י
Rashi gave that other explanation in the משנה, it sounds like what
the גמרא's Gemara saying, that sixteen kilometers is, you know, I guess
on a clear day, and again assuming basically you're on a height
or at least everything is flat, better you're on a height and
they're flat. Anyway, you can see sixteen kilometers. So therefore, since it
speaks about the מונה, moneh, the counter, being able to pass them
under, they understand that you have to be able to conceptually see
them all as one. There has to be as if there was
a shepherd who was able to see them all and only then
would they be considered one flock. Okay, so, מצטרפין, mitztarfin, I mean
in a way it's, you know, obviously very important qualification. I mean
not only is it a leniency but it also makes the whole
thing practical, right? Otherwise you'd have to bring all your sheep together
from Tel Aviv and- and Jaffa and Jerusalem and whatever and be,
you know, so this is realistically what does it mean to be
one flock?
So now, let's take a look. מצטרפין, Mitztarfin,
so the גמרא Gemara says, so it says thirty-two אמות- מיל apart
do not, but if there's one in the middle they do. So
the גמרא Gemara says שלשים ושנים הוא דלא מצטרפי, shloshim u'shnayim hu
d'lo mitztarfi, thirty-two is don't combine, הא בציר מהכי מצטרפי, ha batzir
meihachi mitztarfi, less than thirty-two would combine? והתנן שש עשרה מיל, v'hatnan
shesh esreh mil, we only said that they only combine within sixteen
מיל. טפי לא, Tfei lo, more than that no. So no, the
גמרא Gemara says you're right, it doesn't mean you need thirty-two not
combine. Anything more than sixteen doesn't combine. ומשום דקבעי למיתני סיפא U'mishum
d'kaba'i l'misni seifa because we wanted then say היו לו באמצע,
even if they were thirty-two מיל apart, if there was- if there
were sheep in the middle, מהני דבאמצע, mahani d'ba'emtza, then it's conceptually
bring them all to the middle, not literally but conceptually. So to
tell you that even if they're thirty-two מיל apart, they could be
considered one flock as long as you have some sheep in the
middle. וכמה,
now how many sheep do you have to have in the middle
in order to conceptually combine them? So אמר רב חמש מכאן וחמש
מכאן וחמש באמצע. Amar Rav chamesh mikan v'chamesh mikan v'chamesh b'emtza. You
have to be able to either direction you go to basically have
ten. So if you have five here and five here and five
in the middle, so since if you went to your left you
would have ten, so that combines with what's on your left. If
you go to your right you have ten, that combines with what
you have on your right and therefore they all combine together.
If you have
nine then you don't- you're not obligated. If you had
five, three, and five, this way isn't ten, this way isn't ten.
Let's say you had seven, three and five, then this and this
combine and you do מעשר בהמה Maaser Behema? on this, but this
gets excluded and you don't do it at all, correct. So רש״י
Rashi says what would be for example if you just had five
animals that were born this year? You wouldn't take מעשר בהמה Ma'aser
Behema on them, you have less than ten. Okay, so the same
is true here, that if there's some that doesn't combine, it's like
they were just born
by themselves and therefore you don't do any מעשר.
maaser Especially if you have more, there's no problem at all, they
all combine. You don't say you do like three separate ones.
Right. Now what I thought you were going to ask was going
to be what happens if even if you have five, five and
five, right, and you combine them all, you're only going to do
one מעשר. maaser So who cares if you're combining two or you're
combining three, you're only going to take one animal, right, one out
of ten or one out of fifteen. So we'll see later that
if you have fifteen and they're all obligated but you're only able
to take one, not two, the remaining five if more sheep are
born before the year is out, right, then the remaining five actually
will do, you'll do another מעשר ma'aser. with them. But if they
were never part of that group at all, then they were never
obligated, then they completely don't, you know, totally skip over the מעשר
with them. So we'll see more about that later, but there will
be a difference even if it's an issue of ten or fifteen
whether you include those five or not. If they're fundamentally obligated, that'll
lead to a later obligation with them. Okay, so that's רב's Rav
position. You have to be able to combine any two points to
get ten and if you don't, it doesn't combine. So therefore it's
possible you only combine with your right, only combine with your left,
don't combine with either, or combine with all, but it has to
be only two points has to get you ten. And only then
are they considered a flock. That's what רב Rav says. Okay. Now,
ושמואל אמר, v'Shmuel amar, שמואל Shmuel says, אפילו חמש מכאן וחמש מכאן
ואחד באמצע. afillu chamesh mikan v'chamesh mikan v'echad b'emtza. Nope,
even if there's five at each side and one in the middle.
That even if when you do one act of combining you don't
yet get ten, they're still considered one. This is close enough to
meet this one, close enough there to make it one, you pull
them all together, you have ten. Okay, you don't have to look
at them in, you know, step-by-step. You can do it all at
the same time and bring them all within, you know, to that
middle point.
And
why? Now he goes back to the verse, at least the גמרא
Gemara, asks this to explain him. חזינן לרועה כמאן דקאי הכא. chazinan
l'roeh k'man d'kai hacha. If you have just one sheep in the
middle, so in theory the shepherd will be wherever there's a sheep
or could be where there's a sheep. So the shepherd could be
with the middle sheep. And since the shepherd could be with the
middle one, so קרינן ביה מונה. karinan bei moneh. So that is
the one who is counting who can see sixteen אמה amah in
each direction. The גמרא's Gemara, logic of why it combines is because
the shepherd can see in sixteen אמה. amah. So שמואל Shmuel says
if there's just one sheep is in the middle, imagine as if
the shepherd were in the middle. Since he can see to the
right and see to the left, that pulls them all together. Okay,
so that's how he understands why they can be pulled together. Because
if you took out a particular person and you just saw them
spread out, right, so then you would, you know, then maybe what
gives greater weight to the middle to pull them together? Maybe you'd
say, hey, there's more sheep over here on the left, that's the
primary flock. So that primary flock maybe can שלעפ shlep this one
with it, but it can't שלעפ shlep the other five that are
so far away. Okay, but if you can imagine that wherever a
sheep is, the shepherd could be there, he's the center figure that
can bring them together. That's שמואל's Shmuel understanding. Okay, so now let's
see which way we're going to prove, like רב Rav or like
שמואל. Shmuel. מיתיבי, meitivei, they'll ask on one of these positions, we'll
see which.
היו לו חמישה מכפר חנניה וחמישה מכפר עותני. hayu lo chamishah mi-Kfar
Chananya v'chamishah mi-Kfar Otni. You had five sheep in the village of
חנניה Chananya and five sheep in the village of עותני. Otni. I
assume, you know, it'd be very interesting to find out where these
actually are and whether how far away they are because the גמרא,
Gemara these are being used as examples. אין מצטרפין, Ein mitztarfin, they
cannot combine because there's more than sixteen אמות apart from one another.
עד שיש לו אחת בציפורי, ad she-yesh lo achat b'Tzippori, unless you
had one sheep in ציפורי Tzippori and that one sheep in, right,
that's ציפורי. Tzippori. And that one sheep that presumably is midpoint or
somewhere between these two and is enough to combine the sheep from
the other two villages. But the key is it says one sheep.
So that seems very clear, like שמואל. Shmuel. So תיובתא דרב, tiyuvta
d'Rav, that's a clear contradiction of רב. Rav. So תרגמה שמואל אליבא
דרב, targemah Shmuel aliba d'Rav, so שמואל Shmuel explained it, it's very,
I always love that תרגמה אליבא דרב. targemah aliba d'Rav. It's like,
you know, it shows that it's all being done לשם שמים, l'shem
shamayim, that not like he's like, 'ha, I beat you.' It's like,
'no, you know, I can defend your position this way even though
I disagree with you, here's how you could get out of it.'
תרגמה שמואל אליבא דרב, targemah Shmuel aliba d'Rav, so he interpreted it
in defense of רב, Rav, כגון שהיו תשעה מכאן ותשעה מכאן ואחד
באמצע. k'gon she-hayu tishah mikan v'tishah mikan v'echad b'emtza.
When did it say that if one is enough? Although it started
by drawing a scenario of five and five, but when it then
said if one is in the middle it's enough, it meant a
different scenario, which is a stretch obviously, and it means if you
had nine and nine and one in the middle, then that would
be enough because then, right, you have nine and one makes ten,
nine and one makes ten. So when is one enough? Not if
you have five and five on the opposite ends, but nine and
nine on the opposite ends.
And that
one... אמר רב פפא לשמואל. Amar Rav Papa le-Shmuel. Now that we're
saying for שמואל Shmuel even one sheep combines, and it's not about
that at two points you get ten, it's about the fact that
that one sheep is as if the shepherd were there. So since
conceptually it's like as if the shepherd were there, maybe there's a
way to make it as if the shepherd were there even if
there were no sheep, or one as if the shepherd was actually
there, but okay, what would you define that, what point in time?
There's not like one exact point in time when you're obligated in
מעשר בהמה, Ma'aser Behema but what other circumstances might make it as
if that is where the shepherd is there? So he says, אפילו
רועה מצרפן, afillu ro'eh metzarfan, even the shepherd.
Now again, what does that mean, the shepherd? So you read this,
it sounds like it means the shepherd happens to be there, but
again, as I said, what point of time are we talking about?
You know, when do you determine it? I mean, מעשר בהמה could
be any, you know, any particular time. So Rashi says it means
the shepherd's house is situated midpoint. Now again, remember, you know, one
way to imagine the scenario being drawn, one way to imagine the
scenario being drawn is, is that I go out with all the
sheep and I take, you know, and some are grazing over there
and some are grazing over there and one happens to be grazing
in the middle. But again, if that were just the case, then
first of all, when I bring them all home, they're all together.
And second of all, why should I go by that one day
I happen to be grazing them far apart? The more, you know,
the better scenario, the more correct scenario is as the ברייתא braita
described it, like I was telling you before, I have some in
יפו Yafo and I have some in Tel Aviv. They're actually located,
you know, and housed in different locations, very far away. And then
it says, so you have one in that village and one in
that, some in that village, some in that village, and some housed
in a middle village. So Rashi understands the issue of the shepherd
the same way, not the shepherd happens to be there on a
given day in the middle point, but his home is in the
middle point. So if happy, which is a good idea if you're
the shepherd to be situated midpoint between the flocks you're going to
have to watch. So if you have these flocks, you know, one
in יפו Yafo and one in ירושלים Yerushalayim and the shepherd lives
between the two and it's sixteen kilometers each way, so that is
enough to combine them according to שמואל Shmuel because conceptually it's the
presence of the shepherd that combines them. Just one minute. So first
we say the shepherd, which Rashi says means where the shepherd lives.
ואפילו, ve-afillu, I don't know, ואפילו כליו של רועה מצרפן, ve-afillu kelav
shel ro'eh metzarfan, even if he doesn't live there, even if he
keeps his, like, his supplies there. Exactly. Rashi says exactly, he keeps
his supplies in a city, in a village that's midpoint. בעי רב
אשי, Ba'ei Rav Ashi, Rav Ashi says, כלבא דרועה מאי? kalba de-ro'eh
mai? Let's say his dog, you know, the sheepdog is situated midpoint.
כיון דקרי ליה ואתי ליה מצרפן? keivan de-kari lei ve-ati lei metzarfan?
Do we say that you don't go after your sheepdog, your sheepdog
comes after you? So therefore it's not like as if you the
shepherd are there when you call it, it comes after you. או
דילמא זימנין דלא אתי ומצרפן? o dilma zimnin de-la ati ve-metzarfan?
Sometimes it doesn't listen when you call it, and you have to
go and get it. So therefore even if your sheepdog is there,
it's like you are there. תיקו, teiku, and we don't have an
answer. Yes, now Charlie, you had a question.
But the context is they're talking about, they're implying that this one
shepherd is going to have the right to graze on hundreds of
square miles of land.
Well, I
mean,
all of New York City is about three hundred square miles. Okay,
but this is an unbelievable amount of land.
Wait a minute. First we're talking about, no, no, no, I don't
know if we're saying that. If you take the example I gave,
right, you have, I mean, I'll just use with contemporary cities, you
have
יפו Yafo and whatever, Tel Aviv and ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, it doesn't
mean he can graze anywhere between Tel Aviv and ירושלים. Yerushalayim. It
means that the owner has sheep in Tel Aviv, sheep in ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. He will go, and he's going to be, you know, in
some midpoint. Some days he'll go to יפו Yafo or Tel Aviv,
he'll take them out into wherever the grazing area is there and
graze them there. Some days he'll go to ירושלים Yerushalayim and take
them out into the grazing area near ירושלים Yerushalayim and graze them
there. Doesn't mean he grazes in the entire radius. It just means
the sheep are all within that radius. So therefore it's like they're
one flock. I don't think we've ever said that it has to
be as if they can graze in the entire radius. We're just
saying since he can see from where he is, or from if
you want to take from one flock to the next, I mean,
before you get to שמואל Shmuel that even moves the flock, that
conceptually brings them together.
I can't see stuff in Midtown Manhattan.
Okay, but I don't know, but I remember when I was a
teenager and I was in my first year in Israel and they
would take you, you know, to a mountain and they would say
on a clear day you can see all the way into the
Jordan, right? So I guess it depends how high up you are,
but I agree, sixteen kilometers to be able to see is pretty
far. It has to be a clear day, you have to be
pretty high. You have to be pretty high.
And you have to see sheep. Exactly.
Right, right, right. Which is why I think the first explanation of
Rashi on the משנה is that it's not, ignores the גמרא, Gemara
but I think it's because the גמרא Gemara is hard to understand.
He says that it's because you could take... takes them up to
sixteen kilometers out of city limits in order to graze them.
Yeah, I mean that you could do in a day.
Right, right, and it
explains how all these sheep can be without a shepherd because there's
a shepherd in ירושלים Yerushalayim but he's not in תל אביב. Tel
Aviv. Yeah, that's just the control of those flocks.
Right, the dogs are really good.
Yeah, but
it's not so conceptual. It's pretty practical if he's saying that the
shepherd's equipment or the dog is there.
It's much more, it's much more concrete.
Right, right, exactly. Yep. All right, good.
I mean, someone has to be watching them the rest of the
time, you know?
I kind of... Yeah, but I get maybe that's the point about
the sheepdog.
Oh, the sheepdogs are really good. The whole time?
Day and night? To make him חייב chayav or to let him
off?
Well, the first idea is to let, the first idea is a
big leniency because we quoted a פסוק. pasuk. Without the פסוק, pasuk,
you would have said the תורה Torah says every time I have
new, new animals, I have to, I have to do it. So
even if they're halfway around the world, I had ten new sheep
this year and I have to give מעשר. So by, so the
first point to say is it's a קולא kula is that if
they're not conceptually one flock, even if you own them all, then
you don't. Then we have to define what are the parameters of
one flock.
So that raises another question. If you had a flock in תל
אביב Tel Aviv and a flock in ירושלים Yerushalayim and you're concerned
about who's the בכור, who's the firstborn...
But the firstborn doesn't have to do with flocks. This is מעשר
בהמה.
I understand, but...
The firstborn is every animal individually. It has nothing to do with
a flock.
Okay, but I understand. But the flock here and there and somebody
gives birth and you're in ירושלים Yerushalayim and the flock that's giving
birth is in תל אביב, Tel Aviv, how do you know who's
the firstborn?
You have the same problem anyway, right? Regardless of where you were.
The firstborn is always the firstborn by the mother. It has nothing
to do with the father. So you always know who the firstborn
is.
But if the mother is in תל אביב Tel Aviv and there's
another mother in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so what?
There are two firstborns. I don't understand.
How do you know if you're not there?
Okay, that's why we had a whole פרק perek which is you
don't know, you know one was pregnant, you don't know which of
them gave birth,
something like that.
Exactly. All right, so now, now we get to the very interesting
issue about the ירדן. Yarden. Let's take a look.
רבי מאיר אומר Rabbi Meir omer, הירדן מפסיק למעשר בהמה. HaYarden mafsik
l'ma'aser behema. The Jordan River is a dividing line. So anything on
one side of the Jordan, the other side of the Jordan, they
don't combine, presumably even if they're within a few מיל of one
another, even if they're exactly on opposite sides of the Jordan. So
אמר רבי אמי לא שנו אלא שאין שם גשר. amar Rabbi Ami,
lo shanu ela she'ein sham gesher. That's only if there's no, if
there's no bridge. אבל יש שם גשר גשר מצרפן. aval yesh sham
gesher, gesher metzarefan. It combines them because it's very practical. It's just
the idea that can't, are you conceptually one flock? So we're saying
if there's no way to get from here to there in any
reasonable way, they're not one flock. But if there is a way
to get from here to there reasonably, they are one flock.
Depending how far away the bridge is from you though, no? Let's
say the bridge is forty miles away from you even though it's
right over...
The sheep, yes, yes, but the sheep are within the sixteen מיל.
We're already assuming that because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is saying the
Jordan is another thing that divides them. So we're assuming they're in
sixteen מיל. So he says the Jordan only divides them if there's
no bridge, right, that allows them to...
But if the
bridge is right here and here... Presumably then the bridge is... correct,
correct, right. Okay. Well, that's an interesting point. I hear your point.
If they're visually close and you can get there but you have
to go out of your way. All right, that's an interesting question.
I was assuming that the bridge also made it that you only
had... Look, let's say they're sixteen מיל as the crow flies but
two hundred מיל as the dog walks, you know what I mean?
You know, you can imagine that too. So...
Like inside the Grand Canyon.
Exactly, exactly. So, yeah, that's a good example. You can do it,
it'll just take you an enormous amount more time. That's a good
question according to רבי אמי. Rabbi Ami. I, you know, or even
before you get to the Jordan is a good question, right? Let's
say they're visually close but practically very distant. Okay, but anyway, he
says still, however you answer that, it's about the practical ability, you
know, the practical closeness. That's what he says.
אלמא משום דלא מקרבן. Alma mishum delo mekarvan. So according to him,
the problem of the Jordan is that you cannot bring them close
to one another. אמהו. Amhu. So מיתיבי. meitivei. So let's look in
the practical issue. So now we're going to ask on this. היו
לו בשני עברי הירדן. Hayu lo bishnei evrei HaYarden. We have a
ברייתא braita that says if you had sheep on both sides of
the Jordan, אילך ואילך, eilech ve'eilech, on each side, או בשני אפטליות.
o bishnei aftaliyot. Or in two different... רש״י Rashi sort of says,
if you look at רש״י, Rashi, I don't know if this is
the right... I don't know if I'm reading it trying to read
it into English. He says אקונטראדאש, acontradas, I think. I do wonder
if it means countries. And then he says שני אפרכיות במלכות אחת.
shnei afrakiyot bemalchut achat. So just under one kingdom but ultimately it's
under two different sort of like governments, you know, two different... So
how does the Artscroll translate it?
אפטליות. aftaliyot.
It doesn't. It doesn't translate אפטליות? aftaliyot? Wait, wait, wait... provinces.
Provinces. Okay, anyway, nice תרגום הלעז.
targum halaz. I mean רש״י. Rashi.
So I assume, I think that means something like countries. Okay, so
meaning, and now we're getting to the point, meaning they could be
physically close but they are in two different countries, right? It's in
like,
you know, what's two countries? New York and Connecticut. Okay, so right,
they could be a mile apart but they're right, but they're in
two different states, two different countries. Okay. כגון של
נמר ונמורי, Kegon shel Namer veNemori, like נמר Namer and נמורי, Nemori,
I have no idea, I did not look up the historical, you
know, relevance of those.
רש״י Rashi says two provinces separated by distance of only a single
mil and says there's a river.
Great. I could have told you that too. Right. He's just... right,
he just quoted רש״י. Rashi. I just said that I don't know.
I did not check any, right, any archaeological or historical reference to
these places. Anyway, fine. So it's New York and Connecticut. אין מצטרפין,
they don't combine. ואין צריך לומר חוץ לארץ וארץ, Ve'ein tzarich lomar
chutz la'aretz va'aretz, how much more so if it's in Israel and
out of Israel, which are, you know, halakhically the most different as
you can define in terms of two different countries. So the upshot
of this is, it does not seem to be... the upshot... it's
annoying, but they don't combine. The upshot of this being that it
seems to have nothing to do with the physical distance, or at
least... meaning, yes, the first point is physical distance, but this issue
of different countries is not about the ability to get from one
place to the other. It's that conceptually they're in different regions and
that's enough to say they don't combine. Okay. So... so where are
we? So then the גמרא Gemara spells it out. וחוצה לארץ וארץ
כמקום שיש גשר דמי. Vechutz la'aretz va'aretz kemakom sheyesh gesher dami. There
are places you can get from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to חוץ
לארץ Chutz la'Aretz without there being any, you know, any river, any
physical obstruction. So it's like... it's like as if there were a
bridge. It's not about physical obstructions. וקתני לא
מצטרפין, Vekatani lo mitztarfin,
they don't combine. So you see, not even if physically they're close,
if they're in different countries, that's considered to be different regions. That's
considered separate flocks. אלא אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן
היינו טעמא דרבי מאיר. Ella amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi
Yochanan hainu ta'ama deRabbi Meir. You're right. It's not about physical, you
know, obstructions. It's... here's the reason of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. דאמר
קרא, De'amar kra, the verse says, this is a verse in יהושע
Yehoshua which speaks about the dividing of the territory to the שבטים,
Shevatim, והירדן גבולו לפאת קדמה. Vehayarden gevulo lif'at kedmah.
The Jordan will be its boundary to the east. הכתוב עשאו גבול
בפני עצמו. Hakatuv asao gevul bifnei atzmo. The Torah says the Jordan
is a boundary point. It's a boundary line. Meaning, yes, now obviously
the point being that we have to assume conceptually that it's not
all about distance. If you talk about one flock or two flocks,
right, like what I gave you the example, and I gave it
to you on purpose to sort of show you how, you know,
how strange it would be. If I have sheep that are born
in New Jersey, and sheep that are born in Connecticut, and sheep
that are born in New York, are you going to say it's
all one flock? So naturally we think when they're in different countries,
different states or
whatever... what? You don't think that way? Okay. But anyway, I think
most of us would naturally think that they... that they are defined...
that they would not be considered one flock. I mean, it's true.
If I actually had my, you know, my farm right on the
boundary line of all of them, that might be different. But anyway,
naturally we, when we categorize and group things, the fact that they're
in different states means we group them differently. So if you understand
that that divides the flocks, then he says, so we look in
יהושע Yehoshua and it tells us that the Jordan serves as a
boundary line. And this gets to the other point, which is: yes,
in הלכה, Halakha, and this is why the Jordan is a particular
חידוש. Chiddush. The first point is: it's not all about distance. If
they're in different regions, if they're in different states, countries, or whatever,
they're different. But the next חידוש Chiddush is: you might say, look,
on the, you know, east side of the Jordan is also halakhically
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay. So why should that be a boundary
line? So it says: no, even though it's halakhically ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, it's called עבר הירדן, Ever haYarden, and there are different הלכות
Halakhot there, and that is enough to be considered a different, you
know, location, and not just location, a different country almost, a different
than... and... and does not combine with stuff that's on the other
side of the Jordan.
Yes. This פסוק Pasuk is referring to the division of ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael among the שבטים. Shevatim. Right.
So... does each שבט... Shevet...
so the גמרא Gemara is about to ask that. Very good. You're
ahead. Because that is true. Meaning, at some point we don't make
every dividing line a division. We don't say different cities are a
division, right? So... that was my... right, that was my other example.
Right. So... so we don't say different cities. So only certain things
are big enough divisions. But the חידוש Chiddush here is: even though
it's all ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, there's still a major difference of
the region, whether it's ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper or עבר הירדן,
Ever haYarden, and that's enough to say they don't combine. Yes?
Tangentially, this is one of the reasons we don't understand what's going
on in the Middle East, because countries, the name of countries so
define the people. There are tribes that define the people. So the
sheep depending upon the borders, we say this... this is a flock
and it isn't a flock. We call people part of countries, that's
the way we think, but that's not the way they think.
Yeah.
It's interesting the difference between New York and Connecticut even though, you
know, practically there aren't that many differences because we're still one strong
federal government that unites us all.
Well, that's what רש״י Rashi says. אפיטליאות Apitlyot are exactly that. They're
under one government, but they're still different provinces. So, you know, that's
the... I mean, I think I did that as a parallel to
how רש״י Rashi explains אפיטליאות. Apitlyot. So let's take a look what
the גמרא Gemara says. אלא מעתה. Ella me'ata. So now the גמרא
Gemara. asks Charlie's question. Charlie, you're joining the ranks here of Michael.
So it says, וטהר הגבול ועלה הגבול. Vetaher hagevul ve'alah hagevul. So
it says the boundary goes this... the boundary goes this way and
the boundary goes that way and it's drawing the boundary line between
all of the tribes, very tribe different when it comes to combining
the flock,
so
הכי נמי hachi nami should we also say אקרא סב גבול בשני
אצבו akra sav gvul bishnei atzbo that every every line is a
separate boundary and that they the flocks are not combined across those
שבטים shevatim lines? שאני התם shani hatam there it's different. אמר קרא
amar kra זאת תהיה לכם הארץ לגבולותיה. zot tihyeh lachem ha'aretz ligvuloteha.
Now we're leaving יהושע Yehoshua and going to דברים Devarim where it
gives the division of the tribes where it gives not the division
of the tribes but it gives the boundaries of the entire land
and it says this will be for you זאת תהיה לכם הארץ
לגבולותיה zot tihyeh lachem ha'aretz ligvuloteha סביב saviv around. כולה ארץ ישראל
גבול אחד. kula Eretz Yisrael gvul echad.
So the entire Israel is these are the boundaries of Israel that's
all defined as one country as one space. Now of course they
also got עבר הירדן Ever HaYarden but here again reemphasizes the point.
Yes עבר הירדן Ever HaYarden has קדושת ארץ ישראל kedushat Eretz Yisrael
to a certain degree but it's not ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper
and when the תורה Torah gives the boundaries of ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael it does not give the boundaries of עבר הירדן. Ever HaYarden.
It gives the boundaries of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So within ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael we're not going to divide it and call it
different locations different countries but עבר הירדן Ever HaYarden will be different
although some tribes got that and although it has קדושה kedusha it
is not ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael it's not the boundaries of Israel.
Okay yes.
So when the kingdom split after the death of שלמה המלך Shlomo
HaMelech and they became two countries? Yes. What would be the halachic
difference?
During that time? During that time maybe אין הכי נמי. ein hachi
nami. I mean and you know the גמרא Gemara in גיטין Gittin
and how about in the Roman times when under the Romans when
right I mean first of all the משניות Mishnayot in זרעים Zeraim
talk about three regions right יהודה וגליל ועבר הירדן Yehuda veGalil veEver
HaYarden and under Roman rule you know things could have have been
under different control so those things all might make a difference right
might reflect political realities so it's true the point is a very
legitimate one and you see that by the use of the word
אבטיליות avtilyot that part of this reflects political realities and part of
this reflects halachic or you know
theological or ideological concepts that ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael עבר הירדן Ever
HaYarden you know whatever the political reality is meaning let's ask the
other question let's say under Roman rule ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and
עבר הירדן Ever HaYarden were all under one you know one government
you know one province Roman province which I think they were right?
I don't know anyway.
At times they were.
Okay would that be enough or would we say no since
conceptually the תורה Torah defines ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and עבר הירדן
Ever HaYarden different that you know both are true. If the practical
political reality defines them different and also how the תורה Torah defines
them you know it's so anyway both of those things are relevant
here. Okay so let's take a look
bottom
line in the גמרא.
Gemara What is ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? Well ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
for one meaning for תרומות ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot עבר הירדן Ever HaYarden
although there's also question בית ראשון בית שני bayit rishon bayit sheni
and so on but עבר הירדן Ever HaYarden might well have קדושה
kedusha relating to תרומות ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot and it also was part
of the inheritance of as we know two and a half tribes
but it's not considered ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper. Now what are
the נפקא מינה'ס nafka minas for that? You know depends on which
הלכה. halacha. For this הלכה halacha you have one but there it's
not about the specialness of being Israel it's just that Israel is
distinct from עבר הירדן. Ever HaYarden. You know it's not about עבר
הירדן Ever HaYarden not being less it's just that it's being distinct.
But there are other areas for example you can't bring ביכורים bikurim
I mean not major things you don't bring ביכורים bikurim from עבר
הירדן. Ever HaYarden. You only bring ביכורים bikurim from ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael proper.
So are the rabbis acknowledging political realities or are they...
Not in the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael עבר הירדן Ever HaYarden it's
not that's what I was saying it's not about political reality it's
about sort of biblical reality you know how the תורה Torah conceptualizes
it but when they talk about the two אבטיליות avtilyot it is
about political reality. So the question is let's say those are in
conflict right do you go by either one of those to define
a division? That's the way it seems to me that you know
you would if either the political reality or the תורה Torah reality
defines these as separate regions that's enough to define them as separate
for this purpose yes.
This came up recently when Rav Elyashiv was quoted as saying that
Jews in Eilat have to observe two days
of יום טוב.
Yom Tov.
Well said well said okay now the
גמרא Gemara says like
this
okay אי הכי ei hachi ירדן נמי Yarden nami ארץ ולא ירדן
Eretz velo Yarden so the גמרא Gemara says if that's true so
why isn't the Jordan it's also considered part of the land meaning
now again it's not exactly clear to me what the question is
because how many sheep are actually on the Jordan itself but why
is it only you know but why is the Jordan itself not
included? So the גמרא Gemara says ארץ Eretz it says זאת תהיה
לכם
הארץ zot tihyeh lachem ha'aretz ולא ירדן velo Yarden and not the
Jordan itself. So the only what's in the land itself and the...
west side is ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper. Okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, where are we? ארץ ולא ירדן. Eretz
v'lo Yarden. בשלמא לרבי חייא בר אבא. Bishlema l'Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba.
So according to רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba who
says that it's not about physical ability to physically bring them together,
but conceptually once one region or another,
היינו דקתני ירדן. hainu d'katani Yarden. That's why our משנה gives the
example of ירדן Yarden because it's only the ירדן Yarden that conceptually
divides them. אלא, Ella,
לרבי אמי, l'Rabbi Ammi, when according to רבי אמי Rabbi Ammi that
it's about the ability to bring them together, לימא לכל הנהרות? leima
l'chol hanaharot? Why just the Jordan? Say if any river divides them,
right? Because you because I mean we're talking without bridges, so say
if any river divides them without bridges, it's not about anything special
about the Jordan. So גמרא Gemara says קשיא, kashya, you're right, that's
difficult. Okay. Clearly all of the evidence says that it's not about
the physical ability to bring them together, it's about the role of
the the about defining one region or two regions. So גמרא Gemara
says now there's a question whether you have לימא כתנאי או כתנאי.
leima kitnai o kitnai. לימא כתנאי leima kitnai means maybe this is
like a debate of תנאים, Tannaim, which means we're going to reject
it. כתנאי kitnai means we're saying it is like a debate of
תנאים, Tannaim, but the reason that they take out the לימא leima
is because the גמרא Gemara gives the debate of תנאים Tannaim and
never comments on it. So it seems like it's happy, meaning it
doesn't reject it. So it seems like it's happy to say. It's
nice not to comment. Well, that's דרשה. Drasha. So it seems like
it seems like it's that's why the issue of the לימא, leima,
whether it seems like the גמרא's Gemara going to say it is,
but it's not saying there's a debate of תנאים Tannaim here. Well,
let's see what let's read what it says. Okay.
Yeah, just to understand. So we're saying according to רבי חייא בר
אבא, Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba, even if there wasn't a bridge and
they're on both sides of the ירדן, Yarden, it wouldn't matter. What?
Right? So רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba says even
if there was a bridge and the and the flock is on
both sides of the ירדן, Yarden, it wouldn't matter and it'd still
be considered two regions. Correct. Correct.
Okay. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, לימא כתנאי או כתנאי.
leima kitnai o kitnai. כי אתם עוברים את הירדן ארצה כנען. ki
atem ovrim et haYarden artza Kena'an. You are passing over the Jordan
into the land of Canaan. ארצה
כנען, artza Kena'an,
ארץ כנען, Eretz Kena'an, ארצה, artza, ארץ
כנען, Eretz Kena'an, right, its land is land of Canaan. ולא הירדן
ארץ כנען, v'lo haYarden Eretz Kena'an, and the Jordan or again, although
I said before the Jordan meaning the Jordan proper, here it seems
like it means the Jordan and the other side of the Jordan.
So the גמרא Gemara before saying right, how do you know that
the land it's so so only the land proper and not the
Jordan and the other side of the Jordan are part or not
the certainly not the other side of the Jordan are part of
the land of Canaan proper. It doesn't mean it doesn't have קדושה,
Kedusha, but not ארץ כנען Eretz Kena'an proper. דברי רבי יהודה בן
בתירא. divrei Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira. That's what רבי יהודה בן בתירא
Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira says. רבי שמעון בן יוחאי אומר, Rabbi Shimon
ben Yochai omer, הרי הוא אומר, harei hu omer, the verse says,
מעבר לירדן יריחו קדמה מזרחה, me'ever l'Yarden Yericho kedma mizracha,
from you know about from over the Jordan of Jericho eastward. So
so it calls it ירדן יריחו, Yarden Yericho, the Jordan of Jericho.
So מה יריחו ארץ כנען, ma Yericho Eretz Kena'an, so it connects
Jericho to the Jordan. The same way Jericho is part of the
land of Canaan, אף ירדן ארץ כנען, af Yarden Eretz Kena'an, even
the Jordan is the land of Canaan. Now again, it's funny because
it seems to be talking about the Jordan, but presumably what's really
relevant here is the עבר הירדן, Ever haYarden, right, is the west
side of the Jordan. I mean the east side of the Jordan,
excuse me. So and that seems to be that they're debating, right,
is that considered one unit or not? And therefore the גמרא Gemara,
says this issue of whether the Jordan divides maybe is this debate
of תנאים Tannaim because what are they debating? Are they debating whether
it has קדושת ארץ ישראל, kedushat Eretz Yisrael, you bring תרומות ומעשרות?
terumot u'ma'asrot? We do we know you bring תרומות ומעשרות, terumot u'ma'asrot,
we know it has sanctity of Israel. Why they wouldn't be debating
you know they've never seen them debate that question. So then what's
the point of debating whether it's ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper or
not? So it assumes the debate is relevant to our issues, whether
it's two regions or one region for our issue. Now notice though,
this is not and this is the problem with the גמרא Gemara.
saying it's a debate of תנאים, Tannaim, that it's not the debate
we were talking about before. The debate we were talking about before
was whether it matters that it's two regions or it only matters
whether you can physically bring them together. This is saying assuming that
it matters that it's two regions, do we say that ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and עבר הירדן Ever haYarden are one region or two
regions? It's not the same, right, you understand it's not the same
as the earlier debate. The earlier debate you had one אמורא Amora
saying I don't care if you call it two regions or one
region, I just want to know if you can physically bring the
sheep together. The bridge. It's
about the bridge. And the other no, it's about two regions. This
question of עבר הירדן Ever haYarden and ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper
is saying it does matter that it's two regions, but even when
we say it matters, we have to determine which what we're going
to call one region and what we're going to call two regions.
So it's not exactly the same debate as before. That's why it's
a little complicated. But anyway, so here you see clearly the thrust
of all of this is against the idea that it's about the
bridge and practical, it's about one region or two regions and about
that the Jordan River, even though עבר הירדן Ever haYarden has קדושת
ארץ ישראל, kedushat Eretz Yisrael, it's not considered ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
proper. I'll give you another example. There's actually like one example as
I told you was this question can you bring ביכורים bikurim from
it? But you know there's this famous book that was written by
a student of the ראש Rosh in the 13th century, which is
called כפתור ופרח. Kaftor Vaferach. It is like you know it's like
this thick, this was at a time you have to understand when
they didn't have printing press, and it's like it brings together he's
like totally was focused on ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, he brought together
every single מצוה. mitzvah. Every single מדרש Midrash in the world relating
to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and he organized it every single discussion.
Even stuff that's like ninety-five percent overlap, he rewrites the entire מדרש.
Midrash. Again you wonder who had the copyists that are copying all
this over. But the part that everybody focuses on is like the
tenth chapter where he discusses the halakhic implications of things like קדושת
ארץ ישראל, Kedushat Eretz Yisrael, non-קדושת ארץ ישראל Kedushat Eretz Yisrael and
he lays out a very important principle there, which is the idea
of the difference between what I'm not sure he uses this terminology,
but basically שם ארץ ישראל Shem Eretz Yisrael meaning what's called Israel,
the land of Israel, and what has the קדושה Kedusha of Israel.
And he says for example the following. There's an opinion in the
גמרא, Gemara right, that after the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, was destroyed,
the first בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash and after the second בית המקדש
was destroyed, there's no longer קדושת ארץ ישראל. Kedushat Eretz Yisrael. So
he says what does that mean there's no longer קדושת ארץ ישראל?
Kedushat Eretz Yisrael? Does that mean that there's no importance about living
in the land of Israel? Does that mean when we say for
example there's a value about being buried in Israel, that that doesn't
apply, do we say that if there's no קדושת ארץ ישראל Kedushat
Eretz Yisrael living in Israel is the same as living in
Newark? Anyway so he says no, he says there's a difference. There's
the land of Israel that was promised to אברהם יצחק ויעקב, Avraham
Yitzchak VeYaakov, that's our
inheritance, and that has a special relationship with God to the people
living in the land of Israel. He says and that there's importance
about being buried there, that has nothing to do with קדושת ארץ
ישראל Kedushat Eretz Yisrael in the halakhic sense. קדושת ארץ ישראל Kedushat
Eretz Yisrael in the halakhic sense is the question about whether the
stuff that grows is חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות Terumot U'Maasrot and
has much more of a limited sense. The same way you can
say that something, the land cannot have קדושה Kedusha and still be
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or have this limited definition of קדושה, Kedusha,
you can say the flip for עבר הירדן. Ever HaYarden. עבר הירדן
Ever HaYarden can have קדושת ארץ ישראל Kedushat Eretz Yisrael in the
sense of being obligated in תרומות ומעשרות, Terumot U'Maasrot, but it still
is not the primary Israel. So for example, if somebody says I
want to be buried in Israel, can you say oh well we'll
bury you in עבר הירדן Ever HaYarden because that was also Israel?
I think intuitively we would see that the answer is no. So
that's a way of understanding here the difference about is עבר הירדן
Ever HaYarden ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper. Now it's not so obvious
because the tribes did get their inheritance in עבר הירדן. Ever HaYarden.
So that does push more to thinking about it as maybe maybe
it's extended Israel, but not ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper. So that's
some of the questions that are here. But for the most halakhic
aspects relating to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael like תרומות ומעשרות, Terumot U'Maasrot,
it applies to עבר הירדן. Ever HaYarden. But here it's still a
question, one region or two regions with this as a relevant application.
Yes.
I wonder if that's the reason why the attempts to settle the
גולן Golan failed. I think
if it's not really has the same sanctity as Israel.
Right, I
hear
you,
but let's not try to use הלכה halakha and whatever to interpret
politics for now. Too controversial-ridden. So let's talk for offline
discussions. Now let's go on, continue in the גמרא. Gemara And let's
take a
look. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן אין ירדן אלא
מבית יריחו ולמטה. Amar Rabba Bar Bar Chana Amar Rabbi Yochanan Ein
Yarden Ella MeBeit Yericho U'Lemata. The only thing that's considered the Jordan,
presumably for dividing the land, is from יריחו Yericho south. יריחו Yericho
north, although it is obviously the same body of
water, is not halakhically considered the Jordan. ולמאי הלכתא, U'LeMai Hilcheta, what's
the נפקא מינה? Nafka Mina? So I said for our purposes, but
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אילימא לנודר, Ilema L'Noder, if
somebody takes a vow, I'm not going to benefit from the water
of the ירדן. Yarden. So can they benefit from the ירדן Yarden
that is above יריחו? Yericho? הלך אחר לשון בני אדם. Halach Achar
Lashon Bnei Adam. You go by what people call it. וכל היכא
דקרו ליה ירדן איתסר ליה. VeChol Heicha DeKarle Lei Yarden Itasar Lei.
Whatever is called the Jordan by people is forbidden if you took
a vow against benefiting from the waters of the Jordan. What, no,
the point would be people call the whole thing the Jordan. So
what are you doing dividing it and limiting it to from יריחו
Yericho south? אלא למעשר בהמה. Ella L'Maaser Behema. So it's obviously for
our purposes. When do we say the Jordan divides it as two
regions when it comes to מעשר בהמה? And that's a little bit
bizarre because since right and now he's going to
do it based on a פסוק. Pasuk. But the point still being
that even if it's not called the Jordan, if you go by
how the תורה Torah has drawn the lines, the תורה Torah draws
the lines of the east boundary of the land of well actually
that's not true. Because the תורה's Torah lines in דברים Devarim actually
when you go over when it's past the כנרת Kinneret I think
it juts out to the east. The תורה's Torah lines in דברים.
Devarim. So maybe that's also why the ירדן Yarden is not what
is significant beyond that point.
Does anybody have I
should have brought a picture of that if we had an ArtScroll
or whatever? No, but do they have a picture of the boundaries
of the boundaries of no that doesn't have a picture
in the ArtScroll. No, no, no, I think in the ArtScroll volume,
I think I'm not remembering exactly, but essentially, right, if this is
the כנרת Kinneret and this is the Jordan or whatever, then the
boundaries get here, they go somewhere like that. Right? So therefore that
might... Of course, where's יריחו Yericho relevant to, relative to the?
Way north south? Way, way almost to the Salt Sea.
Really? Yeah. So then it's hard, very hard to understand then what
that means, why we would go, why we would say the thing
above is not, is not the ירדן Yarden for מעשר בהמה since
in the end, although we did quote a פסוק pasuk about the
ירדן, Yarden, it also seems to be about what's considered ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael versus חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. So it's not exactly clear.
Mt. Hermon and everything? Yeah. All right. So anyway, so let's take
a look why he says this. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi,
we taught similarly, ירדן יוצא ממערת פמיאס, Yarden yotzei mi-me'arat Pamyas, and
the Jordan comes out from the cave of פמיאס, Pamyas, that's in
this north, ומהלך בימה של סיבכי u-mahalach be-yamah shel Sivchi and goes
passes through the ocean, probably the, you know, sea of סיבכי, Sivchi,
ובימה של טבריה, u-be-yamah shel Tveriah,
the Sea of Tiberias, which is I assume the כנרת, Kinneret, right?
Right, okay, yeah. ובימה של סדום, u-be-yamah shel Sdom, okay, which is
the Dead Sea, right? והולך ונופל לים הגדול ve-holech ve-nofel le-Yam HaGadol
and then it goes and falls into the Mediterranean. Does it?
Well, no, it's not.
No, it means the Gulf of Aqaba.
No, it doesn't.
It doesn't
go into the Mediterranean.
No.
It ends at the Salt Sea.
It ends at the Salt Sea. Does anything come out of the
Salt Sea?
No, that's why it's salty. Exactly.
Okay, anyway, moving on. ואין ירדן ve-ein Yarden and it's only considered
the Jordan אלא מבית יריחו ולמטה, ela mi-beit Yericho u-lematah, from יריחו
Yericho south. Okay,
so here you see that it's only the Jordan from יריחו Yericho
south. But again, why that should be true for מעשר בהמה is
not clear to me based on the fact that, yes, you know,
a, well, let's take a look. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר
רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan. Anyway, so
why is it? So the reason is he gets it from the
פסוק. pasuk. The פסוק pasuk says ירדן יריחו. Yarden Yericho. So, only
it's only considered the ירדן Yarden from יריחו Yericho onward because the
verse refers to it as the Jordan of יריחו. Yericho. Okay, so
it's not the other way around? It's the upper. Hey, I don't
know that, but b, as I've already said, it's not clear to
me what... okay. It's not the source.
They identify the source as north. I'm just curious if they...
the source has to be north. It can't be coming from the
Dead Sea going up. It has to go from the north going
down. Anyway, as I said, as I said, okay, okay, as I
said, I don't understand, I understand why you might say in a
formal way that it's only called the ירדן Yarden from יריחו Yericho
south based on the פסוק, pasuk, but given that the idea of
dividing it has to do with ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, חוץ לארץ,
Chutz La'aretz, it's hard for me to understand why it should not
serve as a dividing line when you go north of יריחו Yericho
as well.
Anyway, it was the dividing line for the two and a half
שבטים. shvatim.
Right. Right. I mean, only when you got, only when you got
above the כנרת Kinneret did it stop being the dividing line.
It actually says here that north of יריחו Yericho that Jordan River,
it says Jordan River north.
I know. But we're just saying הלכתית halachically it's not considered the
Jordan River north of יריחו. Yericho. So then you have Jordan on
one side
and Jordan on the other side?
That's, they would divide. Right. Okay, please let's just focus now and
get a little bit further. Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan,
אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan. Now that we're talking about the ירדן, Yarden,
we have a little bit of an Aggadic digression. למה נקרא שמו
ירדן, Lamah nikra shemo Yarden, why is it called the Jordan? שיירד
מדן, she-yared mi-Dan, get it? ירד דן. yarad Dan. It comes from
דן. Dan. The tribe of דן Dan was north, it starts north
and it comes down. אמר ליה רב אבא לרב אשי, Amar lei
Rav Abba le-Rav Ashi, אתון מהתם מתניתו לה, atun me-hatam matnitu lah,
you learn, you know that it starts in דן Dan based on
what you, how you unpack the word. אנן מהכא מתנינא לה, anan
me-hacha matnina lah, we get it from here. ויקראו ללשם דן בשם
דן אביהם, vayi-kre'u le-Leshem Dan be-shem Dan avihem, they called לשם Leshem
דן Dan after the name of דן Dan their father. Okay, that's,
and then it goes on, and then ואמר רבי יצחק, ve-amar Rabbi
Yitzchak, לשם זו פמיאס, Leshem zu Pamyas, and רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak
teaches לשם Leshem is פמיאס. Pamyas. And we know ותניא יוצא ירדן
ממערת פמיאס, ve-tanya yotzei Yarden mi-me'arat Pamyas, so since לשם Leshem is
פמיאס Pamyas and the Jordan comes out of there, we
can a plus b plus c, we figure out that the Jordan
originates in דן. Dan. אמר רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, זכרותיה דירדנא,
Zachrutei di-Yardena, the strength or now רבקה, Rivka, you'll appreciate this or
not, that the word used here for saying the essence, the, you
know, or the quintessence might be even the better word here, is
זכרותיה, zachrutei, the maleness. So the זכרותיה, zachrutei, the quintessence or the
essence of the ירדן Yarden ממערת פמיאס, mi-me'arat Pamyas, it's where it
comes out from its origin in the cave of פמיאס. Pamyas. היכא
דאמר, Heicha de-amar, so if somebody says לא שתיתי מיא ממערת פמיאס,
lo shatitei maya mi-me'arat Pamyas, איצטלי בכלי ירדנא. itztilei bi-kli Yardena. If
somebody says I won't drink the waters from the cave of פמיאס,
Pamyas, so since it all starts in פמיאס, Pamyas, he can't drink
the waters from any part of the Jordan River because it all
starts there. Okay, now זכרותא דדמא, zachruta de-dama, the essence of blood
כבדא kavda is the liver, meaning that's where it sort of it
all like, you know, that's filled with blood. כרבי יצחק, Ke-Rabbi Yitzchak,
like Rabbi Yitzchak, דאמר רבי יצחק, de-amar Rabbi Yitzchak, כבד שנימוח, kaved
she-nimuach, if you have a human liver after a person died and
it dissolved, מטמא ברביעית, metamei be-revi'it, it's treated like blood itself and
the same way blood causes טומאה tumah under a tent, under a
roof with a רביעית, revi'it, a dissolved liver the same, it's considered
to be the quintessence of blood.
Okay, זכרותא דמיא zachruta de-maya פרת, Prat, the essence of all of
all waters is the river
Euphrates because we've got to understand that all the rivers in the
world basically come from... of the Euphrates. דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב,
D'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, הנודר ממי פרת, hanoder mimei Prat, if
somebody takes a vow not to benefit from the waters of the
Euphrates, אסור בכל מימי שבעולם. assur bechol meimei sheba'olam. Can't drink any
water in the world because they understand that all waters ultimately originate
from the Euphrates.
Now, היכי דמי? heichi dami? So the Gemara says what's the case?
אילימא דאמר לא שתינא ממי דפרת, Ilima d'amar lo shtina mimei d'Prat,
if somebody says I won't drink from the waters of the Euphrates,
מי פרת הוא דלא שתינא. mei Prat hu d'lo shtina. So we
go by what the language means and that doesn't mean water that
originated in the Euphrates, it means what I would call water of
the Euphrates as when taken directly from the Euphrates. That's what that
phrase would mean. הא מנהרא אחרינא שתינא, Ha minhara achrina shtina, I
can drink from other rivers. אלא דאמר, Ela d'amar, so what happened
was I said, לא שתינא ממיא דאתו מפרת, lo shtina mimaya d'atu
miPrat, I won't drink from waters that came from the Euphrates. And
we are saying that all waters in the world originate from the
Euphrates. דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, D'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, כל
נהראות למטה משלוש נהראות, kol naharot lemata mishalosh naharot, all rivers in
the world are below the three rivers, the three rivers mentioned in
the Torah in Gan Eden, right? Chidekel, what is it? הנהר הראשון,
hanahar harishon, Pishon, Gichon, and Chidekel. No, there's four.
There's four. ונהר יוצא מעדן להשקות את הגן ומשם יפרד והיה לארבעה
ראשים שם האחד פישון, Venahar yotzei me'Eden lehashkot et hagan umisham yipared
vehaya le'arba'ah rashim shem ha'echad Pishon, Pishon, Gichon, and Chidekel. Okay. So
those are, so those three, all rivers are below them, meaning they
feed into all rivers. So all rivers get their water from those
three. תלתא נהראות למטה מפרת, Tlata naharot lemata miPrat, and those three
are below the Euphrates. The Euphrates is the one that
from its waters come all their waters and their waters and their
waters. You mean this literally?
You mean that you really, you know, if you're in New York,
you can't drink from the Hudson?
I don't know. I don't know.
So the Gemara says,
והאיכא עינא דמדיין?
Veha'ika eina d'Madayan? Ah, aren't there wellsprings that are very high up
in the mountains that are clearly higher than the Euphrates? So the
Gemara says, אמר רב משארשיא, Amar Rav Mesharshiya, הנהו סולמי דפרת הנהו.
hanhu sulamei d'Prat hanhu. Those are the ladders of Prat, meaning yet
somehow the waters of Prat go up under, you know, under the
ground and even come out in those high wellsprings high up in
the mountains. So the Gemara says, הכתיב והנהר הרביעי הוא פרת? Haktiv
vehanahar harevi'i hu Prat? Doesn't it say the fourth one is the
Euphrates, which means presumably it's lower than the other
three? So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק ואי תימא רב אחא בר
יעקב, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak ve'iteima Rav Acha bar Yaakov, הוא
פרת hu Prat דמעיקרא. d'me'ikara. That we mentioned earlier, meaning when it
says נהר יוצא מעדן nahar yotzei me'Eden and then it says the
fourth one, it is the Prat, it means it was the first
one that was mentioned, the נהר יוצא מעדן. nahar yotzei me'Eden. As
Tosafot says, what it really, what this means is not only it
was mentioned first, but it means that when it says it divides
into four tributaries, that it means that the, when we say the
fourth is Prat, we mean that was the original. We said there's
one that divides into four, but we're mentioning Prat last, but we're
saying that is still the continuation of the original that is the
Euphrates. So not four plus one, it's one becomes four, but Prat
is the extension of the original. Okay. תניא ותנא בברייתא, Tanya vetana
babraita, רבי מאיר אומר, יובל שמו. Yuval shemo. It's really not called
Prat, its real original name is Yuval. Okay, שנאמר, shene'emar, והיה כעץ
שתול על מים, vehaya ke'etz shatul al mayim,
you'll be like a tree planted on the waters, ועל יובל ישלח
שרשיו, ve'al Yuval yishlach sharashav,
here understanding Yuval as a proper name. By the Yuval will the
roots of the tree go down. And they understand that this is
referring to the עץ הדעת Etz HaDa'at in Gan Eden, okay, not
just a vision for the future, but the עץ הדעת Etz HaDa'at
in Gan Eden or the עץ החיים Etz HaChayim in Gan Eden.
So therefore, what was in Gan Eden? The Euphrates. So you see
the name of the river is Yuval. ולמה נקרא שמו פרת? Velama
nikra shemo Prat? So then why was it called Prat? That's descriptive.
That's not a proper name. שמימיו פרין ורבין, shemeimav parin verabin, because
its waters are fruitful and multiply, meaning that it constantly, like particularly
in the rainy season as we'll discuss, the waters increase, so Prat
is פרין ורבין, parin verabin, increase. It's a descriptive name, not a
proper name. Maybe we can just go two more minutes to finish
to the Mishnah. מסייע ליה לשמואל. Mesayei lei leShmuel.
Now this idea that we're saying that the Euphrates itself increases and
we're not claiming, meaning not from rain, but presumably its natural characteristic
to increase, supports Shmuel. דאמר שמואל, D'amar Shmuel, נהרא מכיפיה מיברך. nahara
meikeifei mivrach. Rivers when they increase, increase from their source, the rock
underneath, the bedrock, meaning that as opposed to what we would say,
which is the rain or the melted snow, he's saying ultimately it's
because more water is coming from natural springs underneath. And I'm sure
it depends river by river. So here we're saying the Euphrates, which
is פרין ורבין, parin verabin, presumably means by itself without the rain,
and that's like Shmuel. Now there's a halakhic significance to this. Let's
take a look.
ופליגא דרב. Upliga d'Rav. This argues on Rav. דאמר רב אמי אמר
רב, D'amar Rav Ami amar Rav, מטרא במערבא, mitra bema'arava, if it's
raining in Eretz Yisrael,
סהדא רבה דתחותיה פרת sahada raba detachotei Prat is that the Euphrates
is a very high water level in Bavel. This assumes A, that
rain is what increases the water level of the Euphrates, but B,
that the Euphrates originates in Israel and goes to... and goes to
בבל, Bavel, which תוספות Tosafot says is clearly not the case, and
he's like, and I spoke to people, they told me it doesn't
work that way, it goes from בבל Bavel to ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. So, okay. We don't exactly know what to do with that,
but anyway for our purposes, what's important is that רב Rav says
that it's the rain that increases the Euphrates and not that it
happens by itself. And now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אבוה
דשמואל, Avuha d'Shmuel, now we get a very interesting halachic application.
עבד להו לבנתיה מקוה ביומי ניסן ומפצי ביומי תשרי. Avad lehu livnatei
mikva beyomei Nissan u'maftzei beyomei Tishrei. So remember שמואל Shmuel lived in
בבל, Bavel, his daughters needed to go to the מקוה. Mikvah. So
what did he do? So when it was ניסן, Nissan, when it
was the spring season which was at the end of the rainy
season, they could not go into the Euphrates. Why couldn't they go
into the Euphrates? Well, A, you could just say they could have
drowned, but anyway, but more what, but halachically the reason is as
the גמרא Gemara will say is the following. First I'll explain it
the accepted way then I'll tell you what רש"י Rashi says. The
accepted way is the following.
When a מקוה, Mikvah, anybody knows what a מקוה Mikvah which has
become collected rainwater, it has to be stationary, it cannot be flowing,
okay? That's a הלכה, Halacha, it has to be stationary. Now if
you have a body of water that is a natural flowing body
of water like a river, it is allowed to be flowing, okay?
So you could be טובל Tovel in a river even though it's
flowing. But let's say it's been very rainy and the majority of
the water in the river is rainwater. So we actually give it
the status as a מקוה Mikvah and not as a river and
that we say that you can only use the river if the
water is standing, which obviously it won't be in the river, because
the majority of the water is rainwater. If
the majority of the water is from underground springs and natural water,
can it be flowing. So the concern of אבוה דשמואל Avuha d'Shmuel
was the following. In ניסן, Nissan, in the spring after all the
rains and all the melted snow, it got so high that he
was concerned that there was more rainwater than natural water and therefore
you can't use it as a מקוה Mikvah because it's flowing. And
therefore he had to make them separate מקוואות Mikvaot that they could
use then they could not be טובל Tovel in the Euphrates, okay?
So he made a מקוה ביומי ניסן, Mikvah beyomei Nissan, in the
spring he made for them
מקוואות Mikvaot ומפצי ביומי תשרי. u'maftzei beyomei Tishrei. תשרי, Tishrei, it was
the rainy season hadn't begun, it had been just after the summer,
so you could be טובל Tovel in the Euphrates, but you needed
mats. What did you need mats for? So either not to get
your feet muddy so you don't have a חציצה Chatzitzah or to
be a protector so you're not naked in front of other people
or afraid people will see you and therefore not do a good
job being טובל. Tovel. So either for privacy or for mats, that's
what he did when it was at the end of the summer.
Okay, so you see that he feels that the rainwater is what
increases it because he was concerned about this issue.
So מקוה ביומי ניסן, Mikvah beyomei Nissan, סבר לה כרב, savar lah
k'Rav, he feels like רב, Rav, דאמר רב אמי אמר רב מיטרא
במערבא סהדא רבא בפרת d'amar Rav Ami amar Rav mitra bema'arava sahada
rabba biPrat that when it's raining in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you
can see it in the Euphrates, which means rain is what increases
it, and therefore since rain increases it, he felt שמא ירבו הנוטפים
על הזוחלים, shema yirbu hanotfim al hazochalim, there will be more rainwater,
נוטפים notfim is drip, זוחלים zochalim is flow, there will be more
rainwater than the water that naturally flows, והוו להו מי גשמים רובא,
vehavu lehu mei geshamim rubba, and the rainwater will be the majority,
and you cannot be טובל Tovel in it when it's running water,
and you therefore if there's too much rainwater you cannot use it
as a מקוה, Mikvah, and therefore he had to make them a
separate מקוה. Mikvah. ומפצי ביומי תשרי u'maftzei beyomei Tishrei and he made
mats in תשרי Tishrei either for the mud or for privacy. ופליגא
דידיה אדידיה, u'peliga didei adidei, now שמואל Shmuel who before said that
the Euphrates comes from its own source, he actually said another statement
that contradicts his own position. Why? Because he said, דאמר שמואל אין
המים מטהרין בזוחלין אלא פרת ביומי תשרי. d'amar Shmuel ein hamayim metaherin
bezochalim ela Prat beyomei Tishrei. He said you cannot use the flowing
water, certainly of the Euphrates, except in תשרי Tishrei at the end
of the summer season. The rest of the time we have to
be considered it's rainwater. So you see that even שמואל Shmuel was
considered that the Euphrates increased not on its own but due to
rainwater. And it seems like he's even maybe stricter than his father,
because his father said that maybe it was only in springtime his
father was concerned about rainwater. שמואל Shmuel was concerned the entire year
except at the very end of the summer season. So here we
have this idea that and actually this is very practical in הלכות
מקוואות Hilchot Mikvaot because if people want to be טובל Tovel in
rivers which sometimes happens, you have to be concerned about what time
of the season is it, has there been a lot of rain?
And if it's flowing water and if it's too much rainwater, then
you cannot use the flowing water of the river, and that this
גמרא Gemara. is very relevant. I want to end, I know we're
over, but just one more minute to say something about רש"י. I've
interpreted this גמרא the way תוספות Tosafot does and רש"י does in
other places. Here רש"י says something even more radical. רש"י says you
know what the problem is, too much rainwater?
Because nowadays we treat women who are נדות Niddot as if they
might be a זבה. Zavah. Now the תורה Torah never tells you
how a נדה Niddah and a זבה Zavah go to the מקוה,
Mikvah, it just says
they
become... not collected rain water. So רש״י Rashi here says in another
place he rejects it, but here he says that a זבה zavah
needs live water, מים חיים, mayim chayim, and therefore a נדה niddah
would need it nowadays because we treat them like זבות. zavos. And
if there's too much rain water, then it's not, then the majority
of it is collected rain water and not live water. And the
problem here is not just that it's moving, that it's flowing, but
that it's not naturally coming from the ground, natural water. Now this
idea comes, came up in a few גאונים, Geonim, it was completely
rejected by the ראשונים. Rishonim. It's not as absurd as it might
think, I mean if you were just say it, I mean not
just conjecture, if you were to say it then you'd say then
we'd have to get rid of all of our מקואות! mikvaos! Right?
You'd have to go to, where are you going to get wells
from? Everyone would have to go to the ocean! But the interesting
thing is if you know about מקואות mikvaos in in the Middle
Ages in Europe, you know that most of their מקואות mikvaos or
many many of their מקואות mikvaos were dug wells. And dug wells
is מים חיים mayim chayim because it's coming from underground. So if
if that's already what you're using as a מקוה, mikvah, it's not
crazy to think that maybe that's required. But thankfully that was completely
rejected and therefore you know that's why we have all the מקואות
mikvaos we have, we don't have to go out and dig wells.
But that's at least one way that רש״י Rashi reads what's going
on here in the גמרא. Okay.
חלה Chala once and for all...